# AMLAN SINHA

¶ 297 Franklin Ave, Princeton, NJ ■ amlans@princeton.edu  $\square$  (929) · 428 · 6138

#### RESEARCH STATEMENT

I am a Ph.D. candidate in Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering at Princeton University, specializing in dynamical systems, optimal control and astrodynamics. My research aims to harness knowledge from dynamical systems and optimal control to develop a theoretical and algorithmic framework to design robust trajectories for low-thrust spacecrafts under operational uncertainty such as partial or complete engine loss in complex multibody dynamical systems during the preliminary mission design phase.

Research Interests: Astrodynamics, Dynamical Systems, Optimal Control, Robust Control

# **EDUCATION**

Princeton University 2020-Present

Doctoral Candidate in Mechanical Engineering Certificates: Computational Science and Engineering

Princeton University May 2020

M.A. in Mechanical Engineering

GPA: 3.61/4.00

Cornell University May 2018

B.S. in Mechanical Engineering, Minor in Aerospace Engineering

GPA: 3.52/4.00 (Cum Laude)

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Beeson Lab Jan 2022 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant, Adviser: Ryne Beeson

Princeton, NJ

- · Quantitatively and qualitatively assess the role of dynamical structures on robust low-thrust spacecraft trajectories in complex multibody dynamical environments,
- · Investigate the structure of optimal solutions for low-thrust non-robust spacecraft trajectories in complex multibody dynamical environments from a global optimization perspective

Rowley Lab Aug 2018 - Dec 2021

Graduate Research Assistant Princeton, NJ

· Developed a Bayesian algorithm to determine optimal control strategies minimizing the worst-case regret for a linear dynamical system with an unknown system parameter with additive gaussian noise.

# CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2024) "On Robust Low Thrust Trajectories and Invariant Manifolds (Part II)," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Broomfield, CO. (accepted, in-preparation)

Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2024) "Analysis of Robust Low Thrust Trajectories For The Power & Propulsion Element to Earth-Moon L2 Southern Near Rectilinear Halo Orbit," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Broomfield, CO. (accepted, in-preparation)

Li, A., Graebner, J., Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2024) "Learning Optimal Control and Dynamical Structure of Global Trajectory Search Problems with Diffusion Models," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Broomfield, CO. (accepted, in-preparation)

Gi Jo, S., Sinha, A., Anderson, A., Graebner, J., Schmitt, J., Palomo, M., Canales Garcia, D., Beeson, R. (2024) "Global Analysis of Optimal Trajectories from Earth-Moon 9:2 Near Rectilinear Halo Orbit to Low-Lunar Orbits," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Broomfield, CO. (accepted, in-preparation)

Sinha, A., Chhabra, A., Beeson, R. (2024) "Debris proliferation modeling and risk analysis for cislunar orbits." International Astronautical Congress, International Astronautical Federation, Milan, Italy. (accepted, in-preparation)

Sinha, A., Chhabra, A., Beeson, R. (2024) "Incorporating orbital debris risk analysis into cislunar orbital procedures and post-mission disposal," International Astronautical Congress, International Astronautical Federation, Milan, Italy. (accepted, in-preparation)

Chhabra, A., Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2024) "Incentivizing adoption of cislunar orbital debris mitigation policies via norms of behaviour," International Astronautical Congress, International Astronautical Federation, Milan, Italy. (accepted, inpreparation)

Olson, A., Sinha, A., Chhabra, A., Fry, S., Ahner, K., Beeson, R. (2024) "A Feasibility Study of Microsat Mission Architectures for Ring Science in the Uranian System," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Orlando, FL.

Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2023) "On Robust Low Thrust Trajectories and Invariant Manifolds," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Big Sky, MT.

Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2023) "Analysis of Robust Low Thrust Trajectories For The Lunar Gateway," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Big Sky, MT.

Li, A., Sinha, A., Beeson, R. (2023) "Amortized Global Search for Efficient Preliminary Trajectory Design with Deep Generative Models," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Big Sky, MT.

Beeson, R., **Sinha, A.**, Jagannatha, B., Bunce, D., and Carroll, D. (2022) "Dynamically Leveraged Automated Multibody (N) Trajectory Optimization," AAS/AIAA Space Flight Mechanics Conference, American Astronautical Society, Charlotte, NC.

# JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

**Sinha, A.**, Eggl, M., Fefferman, C., Rowley, C.W. (in preparation) "Optimal control for a scalar linear dynamical system with unknown parameter."

# FELLOWSHIPS, AWARDS AND HONORS

C.V. Starr Fellowship, Merit Fellowship, Princeton University (2020)

Graduate Teaching Fellowship, Merit Fellowship, Princeton University (2020)

University Administrative Fellowship, Professional Development Fellowship, Princeton University (2019)

Engineering Learning Initiative, Summer Research Fellowship, Cornell University (2015-17)

Cornell University Scholarship, Full-Ride Undergraduate Scholarship, Cornell University (2014-18)

\$95,000

N/A

\$1,000

\$12,000

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

# **Graduate Teaching Assistant**

2018-Present Princeton, NJ

Princeton University

- · MAE 206 (Engineering Dynamics)
- · MAE 342 (Space Systems Design)
- · MAE 433 (Automatic Control Systems)
- · MAE 501 (Mathematical Methods of Engineering Analysis)

### Undergraduate Teaching Assistant

Cornell University

2014-2018

Ithaca, NY

- · ENGRG 1112 (Practical Computing in Engineering)
- · MAE 2210 (Thermodynamics)
- · MAE 2030 (Engineering Dynamics)
- · MAE 3260 (System Dynamics)

### OUTREACH AND LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE

Instructor (Math), Garden State Youth Correctional Facility, Crosswicks, NJ

Aug 2021-Present

Co-Founder, Start Smart (a program for low-income students from Bangladesh)

May 2020-Present

Sustainability Chair, Graduate Student Committe (MAE), Princeton, NJ

Jan 2020-July 2021

# RELEVANT COURSEWORK

Classical Mechanics, Dynamical Systems, Optimal Control, Numerical Analysis, Linear Programming, Convex Optimization, Machine Learning

# TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Computer Languages Python, C, C++, Matlab

Tools Bash, Git, Latex, Mathematica, Jira

**Design and Fabrication** Solidworks, ANSYS, Arduino, Raspberry Pi

Research Skills Classical Mechanics, Dynamical Systems, Optimal Control, Optimization,
High Performance Computing, Model Reduction, Time-Series Analysis